Preliminary Guide to the National Coalition of Abortion Providers Records, 1990-2009
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
National Coalition of Abortion Providers records 1990-2009
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
National Coalition of Abortion Providers
5.6 linear feet Extent: 3450 Items
The National Coalition of Abortion Providers (NCAP) was founded in 1990 as a pro-choice organization that represented the political interests of over 200 independent abortion providers throughout the United States. Collection includes NCAP newsletters; pro-life organization files with news clippings and other materials; partial birth abortion legislation and debate information; training documents, and other administration materials. Also includes printed and audiovisual materials from other pro-choice groups. Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
RL.00932
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The National Coalition of Abortion Providers Records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2009, 2010, and 2012.
Historical Note
The National Coalition of Abortion Providers (NCAP) was founded in 1990 and was based in Washington, D.C. It was a trade organization representing independent abortion providers in the United States, and was formed as a response to the success of Planned Parenthood, as well as to offer independent clinics a means of representation in Washington.
From its inception in 1990, NCAP was led by executive director Ron Fitzsimmons, who lobbied on providers' behalf and also organized annual meetings and other activities. Fitzsimmons received nationwide attention due to his remarks on the partial-birth abortion ban debate, including an interview with the New York Times in 1997, in which he admitted to lying about the prevalence of the procedure. Despite the media storm and the political backfire against the pro-choice movement, he remained at NCAP until 2004. He was followed by Jane Bovard (2004-2005) and Steven Emmert (2005-2007).
The National Coalition of Abortion Providers dissolved and merged with the Abortion Conversation Project to form the Abortion Care Network, which began operations in 2008.
Collection Overview
Accession (2009-0210) (4.8 lin. ft.; 3200 items; dated 1990-2008) includes NCAP newsletters; pro-life organization files with news clippings and other materials; partial birth abortion legislation and debate information; and other administration materials.
Accession (2010-0156) (0.6 lin. ft.; 50 items; dated 1990-2009) includes pro-choice audiovisual and printed materials from a variety of pro-choice women's health organizations, including NARAL, the Center for Reproductive Rights, and the Feminist Majority Foundation.
Accession (2011-0049) (1.2 lin. ft.; 900 items; dated 1989-2009 and undated) includes general administrative and financial files; conference files; files documenting the transition from NCAP to the Abortion Care Network; membership files; outreach and promotional material; print material; and media (some of which has been removed to Duke's Electronic Records Server for preservation).
Accession (2012-0170) (0.2 lin. ft.; 200 items; dated 1994-2008) includes legislative files, along with training documents and projects.
Subject Headings
Fitzsimmons, Ron; National Coalition of Abortion Providers; Abortion Care Network; Unborn children (Law); Right to life; Abortion -- Law and legislation; Pro-choice movement -- United States; Pro-life movement -- United States; Dilation and extraction abortion -- law and legislation -- United States; Abortion services; Abortion counseling; Videocassettes; DVDs
Related Material
The Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture also holds the records of the Abortion Care Network and the Abortion Conversation Project, as well as the personal papers of Peg Johnston, a founding member of these groups.
Contents of Collection
- Accession (2009-0210), (5 boxes)
  Accession (2009-0233) (4.8 lin. ft.; 3200 items; dated 1990-2008) includes NCAP newsletters; pro-life organization files with news clippings and other materials; partial birth abortion legislation and debate information; and other administration materials.
  - February 2006 (Box 1)
  - Newsletters, 1990-1993 (5 folders) (Box 1)
  - New York Times 1960-1979 (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Promoting Post Abortion Emotional Health: Engaging our Communities, an online discussion course with the Abortion Conversation Project, July 6-August 17, 2005 (binder) (Box 1)
  - Partial Birth Abortion: news and articles, 1995-2003 (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - Freedom of Access to Clinics Entrances Act (FACE), 1993-2000 (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Partial Birth Abortion: correspondence/miscellaneous, 1995-2003 (Box 2)
  - Partial Birth Abortion: legislative, 1992-1998 (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Bufferzones Access Laws Stalking Picketing, 1991-2004 (Box 2)
  - Planned Parenthood v. American Coalition of Life Activists, 1999 (Box 2)
  - Ron Fitzsimmons, 2000s (Box 3)
  - News clippings, wanted posters for violent anti-abortionists, 1990s-2000s (Box 3)
  - Pro-life articles, publications, and clippings, 1990s-2000s (Box 3)
  - Abortion conversations with doctors, 2000s (Box 3)
  - Anti-abortion violence, 1990s (Box 3)
  - Advanced Bioscience Resources (ABR) (Box 3)
  - Advocates for Life Ministries (Box 3)
  - Anti-abortion letters and articles, 1990s-2000s (Box 3)
  - American Life League, 1999 (Box 3)
  - Community Development Block Grant (CDBG) (Box 3)
  - Elliot Institute-After Abortion (Box 3)
  - Choose Life license plates (Box 3)
  - Army of God (Box 3)
  - Feminists for Life of America (Box 3)
  - Lambs of Christ (Box 3)
  - Memorials for the unborn (Box 3)
  - Dr. David Gunn (Box 3)
  - Paul Hill (Box 3)
  - Nuremburg Files website (Box 3)
  - Priests for Life (Box 3)
  - Rescue America, 1993-1994 (Box 3)
  - National Abortion Federation (Box 3)
  - Operation Rescue (Box 3)
  - Life Dynamics (Box 3)
  - Eric Harrah (Box 3)
  - RICO (racketeering) (Box 3)
  - Human Life International (Box 3)
  - Strategic Plan, 2000 and 2005 (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Promoting Post-Abortion Emotional Health, online discussion, 2005 (Box 3)
  - Abortion Conversation Project, online discussion, 2004 (Box 3)
  - Member directory (Box 3)
  - Newsletters, 1990-2000 (3 folders) (Box 3)
  - 2 videotapes:
    - Fetal Tissue Hearing, 2000 (Box 3)
    - Promoting a National Conversation on Abortion (Box 3)
  - Newsletters, 2000-2008 (Box 4)
  - Partial Birth Abortion: current news/articles, 1997-2004 (Box 4)
  - Crisis Pregnancy Centers, 1991-2003 (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - Ruth Arick (Box 4)
  - Memos, 2000s (Box 4)
  - CT Corporation (Box 4)
  - Eviction lease issues, 1995 (Box 4)
  - Executive director search committee, 2004 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 2005 (Box 4)
  - Somnia contract, 2007 (Box 4)
  - Translation services, 2003 (Box 4)
  - Strategic plan, 2000 (Box 4)
  - NCAP.com (Box 4)
  - NCAP brochure (Box 4)
  - NCAP buttons:
    - We Trust Women (Box 4)
    - George Tiller, 2009 (Box 4)
  - Newsletters, 1994-2007 (Box 5)
  - Notes and clippings for writing newsletters (Box 5)
  - Short-term Relationship Counseling, Planned Parenthood (Box 5)
  - Trauma, Postabortion (Box 5)
  - The Marketing of Aborted Babies: A Report, Life Dynamics, Inc., 2000 (Box 5)
  - From your future patients, NCAP, 2004 (Box 5)
  - Strategic Plan binder (Box 6)
  - Partial Birth Abortion: legislative documents, 1998-2002 (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - How to Talk About Abortion, Catholics for a Free Choice (Box 6)
- Accession (2010-0156), 1990-2009 and undated, (1 box)
  Addition includes printed materials from various pro-choice groups, including NARAL, the Center for Reproductive Rights, NOW, and the National Abortion Federation. Also includes DVDs and VHS cassette tapes with abortion-themed programs.
  - VHS cassettes (7 tapes) (Box 7)
    - Never Go Back: The Threat to Legalized Abortion, Feminist Majority Foundation, undated (Box 7)
    - Finkel, 1998 Nov (Box 7)
    - Murder on Abortion Row, Frontline, undated (Box 7)
    - Abortion Denied, Feminist Majority Foundation, 1990 (Box 7)
    - Promoting a National Conversation on Abortion, NCAP, undated (Box 7)
    - In a Just World: Abortion, Contraception, and World Religion, The Duncan Group, 2003 (Box 7)
    - The Abortion Experience, Chip Taylor Communications, 1991 (Box 7)
  - DVDs (3 discs)
    - PBS' To the Contrary on Limits on Choice, Persephone Productions, 2005 (Box 7)
    - Legislative Briefing, NARAL, 2008 (Box 7)
    - Legislative Briefing, NARAL, 2009 (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous printed materials (NOW, NAF, NNAF), 1996-2008 (Box 7)
  - What if Roe Fell?, Center for Reproductive Rights, 2007 (Box 7)
  - NARAL printed materials
    - Congressional reports, 2007-2008 (Box 7)
    - Printouts on women's health and pro-choice issues, undated (Box 7)
    - Action Kits, 2000-2007 (Box 7)
- Accession (2011-0049), 1989-2009 and undated, (2 boxes)
  Accession (2011-0049) (1.2 lin. ft.; 900 items; dated 1989-2009 and undated) includes general administrative and financial files; conference files; files documenting the transition from NCAP to the Abortion Care Network; membership files; outreach and promotional material; print material; and media (some of which has been removed to Duke's Electronic Records Server for preservation).
  - Administrative material, 2004-2006, (2 folders) (Box 8)
  - Annual meetings, 2002-2007 (Box 8)
  - Clippings, 1989-2009 (Box 8)
  - Digital Media: NARAL Legislative Briefing, 2009, and NCAP Media, 2001 (removed) (Box 8)
  - Ephemera (Box 8)
  - NCAP-Abortion Care Network Transition (Box 8)
  - Financials, 2009 (Box 8)
  - Membership and financials, 2007 (Box 8)
  - "Message" material (3 of 4 folders) (Box 8)
  - "Message" material (folder 4 of 4) (Box 9)
  - NAF Publications, 1997-1999 (Box 9)
  - NARAL Reproductive Rights Issues Manual, 2003 (Box 9)
  - NCAP Survivor Party Mix (CD) (Box 9)
  - Notes from Patients for Hearts Project (Box 9)
  - Presentations by Peg Johnston, 2004 (Box 9)
  - Promoting a National Conversation on Abortion (VHS tape) (Box 9)
  - Research and administrative material, 2001-2005 and undated (Box 9)
  - Ron Fitzsimmons (Box 9)
  - The Wisdom of Abortion (Box 9)
- Accession (2012-0170), 1994-2008, (1 box)
  Accession (2012-0170) (0.2 lin. ft.; 200 items; dated 1994-2008) includes legislative files, along with training documents and projects.
  - Legislative files and training documents (Box 10)
  - Abortion U (Box 10)
  - Election related activity (Box 10)
  - Legislative advocacy (Box 10)
  - Lobbying reports, 2001-2004 (Box 10)
  - Provider Assistance and Support Project (Box 10)
  - Yanow abortion training (Box 10)